Maybe a year passes, nothing. One day, he's approached by a gentleman who offers to take him to lunch, then to dinner, to breakfast. He meets this dynamic group of people, and they give him a break. He's given a bit of money to buy himself some new clothes, money to send back home to his family. He is introduced to this young woman. He eventually gets married. He starts this new life. He has a purpose in life. One beautiful day in Mogadishu, under an azure blue sky, a car bomb goes off. That small town kid with the big city dreams was the suicide bomber, and that dynamic group of people were al Shabaab, a terrorist organization linked to al Qaeda. So how does the story of a small town kid just trying to make it big in the city end up with him blowing himself up? He was waiting. He was waiting for an opportunity, waiting to begin his future, waiting for a way forward, and this was the first thing that came along. This was the first thing that pulled him out of what we call waithood. And his story repeats itself in urban centers around the world. It is the story of the disenfranchised, unemployed urban youth who sparks riots in Johannesburg, sparks riots in London, who reaches out for something other than waithood. For young people, the promise of the city, the big city dream is that of opportunity, of jobs, of wealth, but young people are not sharing in the prosperity of their cities. Often it's youth who suffer from the highest unemployment rates. By 2030, three out of five people living in cities will be under the age of 18. If we do not include young people in the growth of our cities, if we do not provide them opportunities, the story of waithood, the gateway to terrorism, to violence, to gangs, will be the story of cities 2.0. And in my city of birth, Mogadishu, 70 percent of young people suffer from unemployment. 70 percent don't work, don't go to school. They pretty much do nothing. I went back to Mogadishu last month, and I went to visit Madina Hospital, the hospital I was born in. I remember standing in front of that bullet-ridden hospital thinking, what if I had never left? What if I had been forced into that same state of waithood? Would I have become a terrorist? I'm not really sure about the answer. My reason for being in Mogadishu that month was actually to host a youth leadership and entrepreneurship summit. I brought together about 90 young Somali leaders. We sat down and brainstormed on solutions to the biggest challenges facing their city. One of the young men in the room was Aden. He went to university in Mogadishu, graduated. There were no jobs, no opportunities. I remember him telling me, because he was a college graduate, unemployed, frustrated, that he was the perfect target for al Shabaab and other terrorist organizations, to be recruited. They sought people like him out. But his story takes a different route. In Mogadishu, the biggest barrier to getting from point A to point B are the roads. Twenty-three years of civil war have completely destroyed the road system, and a motorbike can be the easiest way to get around. Aden saw an opportunity and seized it. He started a motorbike company. He began renting out motorbikes to local residents who couldn't normally afford them. He bought 10 bikes, with the help of family and friends, and his dream is to eventually expand to several hundred within the next three years. How is this story different? What makes his story different? I believe it is his ability to identify and seize a new opportunity. It's entrepreneurship, and I believe entrepreneurship can be the most powerful tool against waithood. It empowers young people to be the creators of the very economic opportunities they are so desperately seeking. And you can train young people to be entrepreneurs. I want to talk to you about a young man who attended one of my meetings, Mohamed Mohamoud, a florist. He was helping me train some of the young people at the summit in entrepreneurship and how to be innovative and how to create a culture of entrepreneurship. He's actually the first florist Mogadishu has seen in over 22 years, and until recently, until Mohamed came along, if you wanted flowers at your wedding, you used plastic bouquets shipped from abroad. If you asked someone, "When was the last time you saw fresh flowers?" for many who grew up under civil war, the answer would be, "Never." So Mohamed saw an opportunity. He started a landscaping and design floral company. He created a farm right outside of Mogadishu, and started growing tulips and lilies, which he said could survive the harsh Mogadishu climate. And he began delivering flowers to weddings, creating gardens at homes and businesses around the city, and he's now working on creating Mogadishu's first public park in 22 years. There's no public park in Mogadishu. He wants to create a space where families, young people, can come together, and, as he says, smell the proverbial roses. And he doesn't grow roses because they use too much water, by the way. So the first step is to inspire young people, and in that room, Mohamed's presence had a really profound impact on the youth in that room. They had never really thought about starting up a business. They've thought about working for an NGO, working for the government, but his story, his innovation, really had a strong impact on them. He forced them to look at their city as a place of opportunity. He empowered them to believe that they could be entrepreneurs, that they could be change makers. By the end of the day, they were coming up with innovative solutions to some of the biggest challenges facing their city. They came up with entrepreneurial solutions to local problems. So inspiring young people and creating a culture of entrepreneurship is a really great step, but young people need capital to make their ideas a reality. They need expertise and mentorship to guide them in developing and launching their businesses. Connect young people with the resources they need, provide them the support they need to go from ideation to creation, and you will create catalysts for urban growth. For me, entrepreneurship is more than just starting up a business. It's about creating a social impact. Mohamed is not simply selling flowers. I believe he is selling hope. His Peace Park, and that's what he calls it, when it's created, will actually transform the way people see their city. Aden hired street kids to help rent out and maintain those bikes for him. He gave them the opportunity to escape the paralysis of waithood. These young entrepreneurs are having a tremendous impact in their cities. So my suggestion is, turn youth into entrepreneurs, incubate and nurture their inherent innovation, and you will have more stories of flowers and Peace Parks than of car bombs and waithood. Thank you. (Applause)
Tras quizá un año trascurrido, nada. Un día se le acerca un señor que le ofrece llevarlo a almorzar, después a cenar, a desayunar. Conoce a un dinámico grupo de personas, que le da un descanso. Recibe un poco de dinero para que se compre ropa nueva, dinero para enviar a casa, a su familia. Le presentan a una joven. Finalmente se casa. Comienza una nueva vida. Tiene un objetivo de vida. Un hermoso día en Mogadishu, bajo un cielo azul, estalla un coche bomba. Ese niño de aquel pequeño pueblo con sueños de la gran cuidad era el terrorista suicida, y ese grupo dinámico de personas eran al Shabaad, una organización terrorista conectada con al Qaeda. Entonces, ¿cómo la historia de un niño de un pequeño pueblo tratando de cumplir sus sueños en la ciudad termina con él inmolándose? Él estaba esperando. Estaba esperando una oportunidad, esperando comenzar su futuro, esperando una perspectiva de futuro, y esto fue lo primero que le llegó. Esto fue lo primero que lo sacó de lo que llamamos "el periodo de espera". Y su historia se repite en centros urbanos alrededor del mundo. Es la historia de los marginados, jóvenes urbanos desempleados que desencadenan disturbios en Johannesburgo, desencadenan disturbios en Londres, que buscan algo mas allá del "periodo de espera". Para los jóvenes, la promesa de la ciudad, el gran sueño de la ciudad es el de la oportunidad, de trabajos, de bienestar, pero los jóvenes no participan en la prosperidad de sus ciudades. A menudo es la juventud la que sufre de las más altas tasas de desempleo. Para el 2030, tres de cada cinco personas que viven en las ciudades serán menores de 18 años. Si no incluimos a los jóvenes en el crecimiento de nuestras ciudades, si no les brindamos oportunidades, la historia del "periodo de espera", la puerta de acceso al terrorismo, a la violencia, a las pandillas, será la historia de las ciudades 2.0. Y en mi ciudad de nacimiento, Mogadishu, el 70% de los jóvenes está desempleado. el 70% no trabaja, no va a la escuela. No hacen prácticamente nada. Volví a Mogadishu el mes pasado, y fui a visitar el Hospital Madina, el hospital donde nací. Recuerdo estar ante ese hospital acribillado a balazos pensando: ¿Y si nunca me hubiera ido? ¿Y si me hubiese visto forzado a estar en ese mismo "periodo de espera"? ¿Me habría convertido en terrorista? No estoy realmente seguro de la respuesta. La razón por la que estuve en Mogadishu ese mes era en realidad para albergar a unos líderes juveniles en una cumbre empresarial. Reuní a unos 90 líderes juveniles somalíes. Nos sentamos y tuvimos una lluvia de ideas sobre las soluciones a los grandes desafíos que enfrenta la ciudad. Uno de los jóvenes en la habitación era Aden. Él fue a la Universidad de Mogadishu, se graduó. No había trabajo, ni oportunidades. Recuerdo cuando él me dijo, que debido a que era un universitario graduado, desempleado, frustrado, era el blanco perfecto para Al Shabaab y otras organizaciones terroristas, para ser reclutado. Buscaban gente como él. Pero esta historia toma un camino diferente. En Mogadishu, el mayor obstáculo para llegar del punto A al B son las calles. Veintitrés años de guerra civil han destruido completamente el sistema vial, y una motocicleta puede ser la manera más fácil de movilizarse. Aden vio una oportunidad y la aprovechó. Comenzó una empresa de motocicletas. Comenzó alquilando motocicletas a los residentes locales quienes normalmente no podían comprarlas. Compró 10 motos, con la ayuda de su familia y amigos, y su sueño es en algún momento expandir a cientos de motos durante los próximos tres años. ¿Por qué es diferente esta historia? ¿Qué hace a esta historia diferente? Creo que su capacidad de identificar y aprovechar una nueva oportunidad. Es el espíritu empresarial, y creo que el espíritu empresarial puede ser la herramienta más poderosa contra el "periodo de espera". Faculta a los jóvenes a ser los creadores de las oportunidades económicas que están buscando tan desesperadamente. Y Uds. pueden entrenar a los jóvenes para ser emprendedores. Quiero hablarles acerca de un hombre joven que asistió a una de mis reuniones, Mohamed Mohamoud, un florista. Estaba ayudándome a entrenar a algunos de los jóvenes en la cumbre de la iniciativa empresarial y cómo ser innovador y cómo crear una cultura de la iniciativa empresarial. De hecho, es el primer florista que Mogadishu ha visto en más de 22 años, y hasta hace poco, hasta que Mohamed llegó, si querías flores para tu boda, utilizabas ramos de plástico enviados desde el extranjero. Si le preguntabas a alguien, "¿Cuándo fue la última vez que viste flores frescas?" para aquellos que crecieron durante la guerra civil, la respuesta sería: "Nunca". Entonces, Mohamed vio una oportunidad. Comenzó una empresa de paisajismo y diseño floral. Creó una granja en las afueras de Mogadishu, y comenzó a cultivar tulipanes y lirios, que según dijo, podrían sobrevivir el duro clima de Mogadishu. Y comenzó la entrega de flores para bodas, creando jardines en las casas, y las empresas de la ciudad, y ahora está trabajando en la creación del primer parque público de Mogadishu en 22 años. No hay parques públicos en Mogadishu. Quiere crear un espacio donde las familias, los jóvenes, pueden ir juntos, y, como él dice, oler las rosas proverbiales. Por cierto, él no cultiva rosas porque utilizan mucha agua. Así que, el primer paso es inspirar a los jóvenes, y en esa sala, la presencia de Mohamed tuvo un impacto realmente profundo en los jóvenes. Ellos nunca habían pensado en iniciar un negocio. Habían pensado en trabajar para una ONG, trabajar para el gobierno, pero su historia, su innovación, realmente tuvo un fuerte impacto sobre ellos. Los obligó a mirar a su ciudad como un lugar de oportunidades. Los alentó a creer que podrían ser empresarios, que podrían ser artífices del cambio. Para el final del día, ya tenían soluciones innovadoras para algunos de los mayores desafíos que enfrenta la ciudad. Idearon soluciones empresariales para problemas locales. Entonces, inspirar a los jóvenes y crear una cultura de espíritu empresarial es realmente un gran paso, pero los jóvenes necesitan capital para hacer sus ideas realidad. Necesitan experiencia y orientación para guiarlos en el desarrollo y puesta en marcha de sus negocios. Conecten a los jóvenes con los recursos que necesitan, bríndenles el apoyo que necesitan para pasar de la concepción a la creación, y crearán catalizadores para el crecimiento urbano. Para mí, el espíritu empresarial es algo más que comenzar un negocio. Es crear un impacto social. Mohamed no está simplemente vendiendo flores. Creo que está vendiendo esperanza. Su Parque de la Paz, así es cómo lo llama, cuando esté creado, transformará la manera en que la gente ve su ciudad. Aden contrató niños de la calle para ayudar a alquilar y a mantener las motos para él. Les dio la oportunidad de escapar de la parálisis del "periodo de espera". Estos jóvenes empresarios están teniendo un tremendo impacto en sus ciudades. Así que mi sugerencia es: conviertan a los jóvenes en empresarios, incuben y alimenten su innovación inherente, y tendrán más historias sobre flores y Parques de la Paz que autos-bomba y "periodos de espera". Gracias. (Aplausos)